<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Listaller.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="sect-Listaller-App-Development-RelayTool">
	<title>Relaytool</title>
		<para>A program to provide a more convenient interface to dlopen/dlsym. It allows you to easily soft link to libraries.</para>

	<section id="relaytool-whatis">
		<title>What is Relaytool?</title>
		<para>This is a program to provide a more convenient interface to dlopen/dlsym.</para>
		<para>It lets you write the same style of code you would when using a normal hard link (-lwhatever), but the symbols
		are actually lazy-linked at runtime. You can use the symbols libwhatever_is_present and libwhatever_symbol_is_present()
		to find out what APIs are actually available at runtime. In other words, the need to use function pointers and lots of
		manual calls to dlsym() is eliminated, and it becomes much simpler to soft link to things as a result.</para>
		<para>If a symbol is missing at runtime and you call it anyway, your application will abort and an error message is printed
		that states which function was called. If a variable is missing at runtime, the value is always -1.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="relaytool-howto">
		<title>How to use Relaytool?</title>
		<para>Replace <userinput>-lfoo</userinput> in your link line with <userinput>relaytool –relay foo -lfoo</userinput>, assuming libfoo is in
		the standard search path (<filename>/lib/, /usr/lib, /usr/local/lib</filename>).
		You can pass entire gcc linker lines to Relaytool, and it will interpret them accordingly.
		Most options will be passed through unchanged onto stdout, but <userinput>-lfoo</userinput>
		options that have a preceeding <userinput>–relay foo</userinput> argument will trigger stub generation and compilation.</para>

		<para>Note that Relaytool will invoke <literal>$CC</literal> (or gcc if it's not set) to compile the stub file silently.
		You will not see any output.</para>

		<para>Alternatively, you can use the <userinput>–replace-all-libs</userinput> option to cause Relaytool to generate a stub file for
		every library given in a <userinput>-lfoo</userinput> directive.
		</para>

		<para>Because Relaytool parses linker options, you can feed the output of pkg-config and other config scripts to it:</para>
		<screen>
			[earth@sun] <userinput>relaytool --relay gtkspell `pkg-config --libs gtkspell-2.0`</userinput>
		</screen>

		<para>The above produces something like this, for example:</para>
		<programlisting>
			<code>-Wl,--export-dynamic -L/opt/gnome26/lib libgtkspell.so.0.0.0.stub.o -laspell -lgtk-x11-2.0 -lgdk-x11-2.0 -latk-1.0
		       -lgdk_pixbuf-2.0 -lm -lpangoxft-1.0 -lpangox-1.0 -lpango-1.0 -lgobject-2.0 -lgmodule-2.0 -ldl -lglib-2.0</code>
		</programlisting>

		<para>Note how -lgtkspell was replaced with libgtkspell.so.0.0.0.stub.o </para>
		<para>On architectures that Relaytool does not support, the -l is passed through along with a couple of defines to provide
		libfoo_is_present and libfoo_symbol_is_present.</para>
		<important>
			<para>Ensure <literal>CFLAGS=”-fPIC”</literal> if the library exports variables, as GOT fixup requires your program to
			use PIC code.</para>
		</important>

		<para>If you want to use Relaytool only for part of a shared library (for instance to make use of symbols available in
		newer versions only) you can use the <userinput>–partial-map</userinput> feature. To use this create a file with a line for
		each symbol, with F for function or V for variable in the first column, like so:</para>
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[In file foo.relaymap:
F some_function
V some_variable]]>
		</programlisting>

		<para>then run:</para>
		<screen>
			[earth@sun] <userinput>relaytool --partial-map foo.relaymap --relay whatever -lwhatever</userinput>
		</screen>

		<para>If you want to hard link to a library but soft link to a few symbols, you can use <userinput>–partial-map</userinput>
		and <userinput>–no-replace</userinput>.
		</para>

		<note>
			<para><userinput>–partial-map</userinput> is currently incompatible with multiple
			<userinput>–relay</userinput> libraries on the same command line. You'll have to separate your libraries
			in different Relaytool calls.
			</para>
		</note>

		<para>If you want Relaytool to only generate the symbols required by your code and not the whole list exported by a library,
		you can use the <userinput>–minimal-list</userinput> feature. It takes as argument the list of your object files, from which it
		derives which symbols for each library are actually needed. For example:
		</para>
		<screen>
			[earth@sun] <userinput>relaytool --minimal-list &quot;foo.o bar.o&quot; --relay mylib -lmylib</userinput>
		</screen>

		<para>This will generate a file exporting only the symbols used in <filename>foo.o</filename> and <filename>bar.o</filename>
		actually found in <filename>mylib</filename> instead of the complete list of symbols exported from <filename>mylib</filename>, which
		can mean big space savings in the final executable.</para>
	</section>
</section>
