<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Listaller.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="sect-Listaller-Enduser-AppInstaller">
	<title>Installing IPK packages</title>
	<para>Learn how you can install an IPK package.</para>

	<section id="enduser-appinstall-install-ipk-gui">
		<title>Installing packages (GUI method)</title>

		<para>
			Installing Listaller packages is really easy. Just make sure you have Listaller installed,
			then follow the steps below.
		</para>

		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Download an IPK package or get it from somewhere else.</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>
					Open the IPK-package with your PackageKit package installer (Apper or GNOME-PackageKit).
					If a Listaller frontent is installed, simply double/single-clicking the package file should already
					launch the right application.
				</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>After the package is opened, just follow the instructions on screen to install it.</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>
					The application is now installed. You should be able to launch it via you application-menu. (Plasma, GNOME-Shell, KRunner, …)
					If there have been problems making the setup work for you, please file a bug against Listaller so we can fix it.
				</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>

		<para>
			Listaller uses a system based on GPG-keys and some other values to check if a package can be trusted, as 3rd-party applications
			can come from any source and it is not certain that they won't contain malicious software.
		</para>
		<para>
			The system administrator has set a minimum trust level for packages. If your package is below this level, you will not be able to
			install the package. By default, unsigned packages can never be installed without lowering the minimum security level.
		</para>

		<para>
			If you have troubles installing an application because of this, you can temporarily change the minimum trust in Listaller's config file,
			or speak to your system administrator.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="enduser-appinstall-install-ipk-cli">
		<title>Installing packages (CLI method)</title>

		<para>
			There are many ways to install an IPK package via the command line. We encourage you to use the <command>lipa</command> application, which is shipped with Listaller,
			but you could also use <command>pkcon</command>, the PackageKit command-line tool.
		</para>

		<section id="enduser-appinstall-lipa">
			<title>Install using lipa</title>
				<para>
					To install the package using <command>lipa</command>, just use the following command:
				</para>
			<screen>
				[earth@sun] <userinput>lipa --install <filename>./packagename_version.ipk</filename></userinput>
			</screen>

			<para><command>lipa</command> will then guide you through the rest of the installation process.</para>
		</section>
		<section id="enduser-appinstall-pkcon">
			<title>Install using pkcon</title>
			<warning>
				<para>
					You should generally prefer using <command>lipa</command> over <command>pkcon</command>, since <command>lipa</command> was specially designed for
					use with Listaller, while <command>pkcon</command> is just a command-line PackageKit client, which does not support stuff like Listaller's
					signature-checking, licenses or private installations.
				</para>
			</warning>

			<para>To install the package using <command>pkcon</command>, you can just do the same as you would do when installing a native distribution package:</para>
			<screen>
				[earth@sun] <userinput>pkcon install-local <filename>./packagename_version.ipk</filename></userinput>
			</screen>

			<para>PackageKit will then perform a <emphasis>shared</emphasis> installation of the Listaller package.</para>

		</section>
	</section>
</section>
